<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in West-chester the viii. of October, 1586 Before the iudges and certain recusantes: wherein the conditions of al heretiques, but especiallie of stubborn and peruerting Papists, are discouered, &amp; the duty of al magistrats concerning such persons, applied &amp; opened by Edward Hutchins, Master of Artes, &amp; Fellowe of Brasennose Colledge.</title>
            <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851777</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851777</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03908)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 711:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in West-chester the viii. of October, 1586 Before the iudges and certain recusantes: wherein the conditions of al heretiques, but especiallie of stubborn and peruerting Papists, are discouered, &amp; the duty of al magistrats concerning such persons, applied &amp; opened by Edward Hutchins, Master of Artes, &amp; Fellowe of Brasennose Colledge.</title>
                  <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be solde in Pauls Church-yard, [by T. Cooke, London] at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1586]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name and place and year of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Westchester.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17068:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17068:1"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVL MASTER THOMAS EGER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON Eſquire, and ſollicitour to the Queenes moſt excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, <hi>grace and peace in</hi> Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS I was at Cheſter requeſted (Right Worſhipful) to beſtow ſom pains in the preſence of certaine Recuſantes (though I knew my ſelfe leaſt able of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers there to diſcharge the matter) yet vpon earneſt intreaty I was at length ouer-intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſupply the roome, and to vndertake a ſute ſo charitable. Since which time it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome deare frinds to craue a copy of my labour: which when they had obtained; they did with earneſt perſwaſion aſſay to moue me to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the ſame to the preſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto though at the firſt I was loth to yeeld, yet at length I was ouercome and reſolued to grant vnto them: eſpecially becauſe I had therein diſcouered the ſhamefull, ſubtil and
<pb facs="tcp:17068:2"/> malicious practiſes of our aduerſaries, the Papiſts, the popes Foxes, who in this our day breath daunger without delay &amp; ſpite the grapes of our Sauiours vine, that hath theſe many yeares fructified, &amp; euen now of gods mercy doth floriſh among vs. That ſo the Popes Foxes may be more throwly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; being knowen, more warily auoided: or rather diligently ſought and made faſt, leaſt their libertie doe worke an vtter waſt to our vine. And foraſmuch as the care of Chriſtes vine hath craued, or rather the malice of the Fox hath forced me to beſtow this my ſmall &amp; vnworthy trauell; as I craue the Chriſtian Reader to take al to the beſt, ſo (Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful) I am bould to requeſt your accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame, as ſome pledge of my thankfulnes to you. Deſiring the Lord God to bleſſe you againſt al the Foxes &amp; litle Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes of Rome, that ſeeke nothing but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our vine, which God continue &amp; keepe to our comfort and his own glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your to command in Chriſt, <hi>EDWARD HVTCHINS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17068:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>It is written in the Second Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Canticles &amp; xv. verſe:</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Take vs the Foxes, the litle Foxes, which deſtroy the vines, for our vines haue ſmale grapes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the premiſes where Chriſt our Sauiour ſawe the readines of the Church his ſpouſe to look to her children, &amp; thereupon gaue her great incouragement to followe and not to faile in her purpoſe: to the end that ſhee might the better proceed in this her godly labour to the gaining and keeping of ſoules: in theſe wordes hee calleth vpon her chiefe pillers to conſider his vines, how they floriſh and beare bloſſomes, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the Foxes and litle Foxes, howe they are eger to waſt them, that ſo they might be taken &amp; preuented. For better proſecution of which wordes I note two points. Firſt a metaphor: 2. the matter: the metaphor is double: in the firſt heretiques are compared to Foxes: in the ſecond the godly are compared to vines. Of the 2. hereafter. Touching the 1. metaphor, as generally in al, ſo in this I note, 1. the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor
<pb facs="tcp:17068:3"/> it ſelfe, the title giuen to heretiques: and ſecondly the reaſon: touching the firſt therefore as heretiques are ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to canker, becauſe they doe corrupt and eate men: ſometimes to leauen, becauſe they doe ſoure them that are ſweet in the faith of Chriſt: ſometimes to dogs, becauſe they haue not only mouthes to barke, but alſo teeth to bite the godly: ſometimes to euil laborers, becauſe they doe labour vnder and for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel to ſowe cockle to choake the Lords corne: ſometimes to rauenous woolues, becauſe howſoeuer they pretend themſelues to bee ſheepe, yet their whole hart is how to deuoure the ſheep: ſo here they are compared to Foxes. In which reſpect as I might at the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to beware their fretting, becauſe they are canker: their ſouring, becauſe they are leauen: their barkings and byting, becauſe they are dogs: the mercileſſe hart that is in them, becauſe they are reuenous woolues: ſo my counſel might be and for this time ſhalbe that you beware the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they are Foxes. But why are heretiques compared to Foxes': Surely they are compared iuſtly to Foxes, &amp; among al hereticks moſt truly do papiſtes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the name of Foxes: of Foxes, becauſe they are vnclean like the Fox: Foxes, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:17068:3"/> they are ſubtil, &amp; crafty like the Foxe: Foxes, becauſe they are rauenous &amp; greedy to deuour like Foxes. For as the Foxe is noted to be an vnclean beaſt, &amp; moſt vnclean when he is moſt hunted: right ſo doth it fal out w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al hereticks, &amp; ſpecially with papiſtes, who are vncleane al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies: euen as the vnclean ſpirit is the father that hath begot them, &amp; the God that alwaies rules them. And as they are vnclean alwaies, ſo they are moſt vncleane, when they are moſt preſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worde &amp; moſt chaſed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Lordes Dogs doe not only find their feete, but follow them: &amp; not only barke after them, but come ſo neere as to bite them: when the godly paſtors take eſpecial care of chriſt his lambs, &amp; to that purpoſe do not only ſpy out falſe and hereticall ſpirits, but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the lambes of Chriſt, that they may not pray vpon them: when to this purpoſe their titles by them are proued vntrue: their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt a nulleſt, their claimes counterfeit, their countenance but the falſe floriſh of a ſeducing ſpirit: oh then, what do they ſhew themſelues to be but Foxes? When they are thus hardlie followed, and to their peril purſued, oh what are they but in proofe, and therefore but in truth titled Foxes? Vncleane ſpirits alwaies, but then moſt vncleane, hauing nothing but a
<pb facs="tcp:17068:4"/> face for a fence, and a mouth for a manner to ſlaunder and barke out the matter. A point eaſie to bee proued by the practiſe of all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, that euer were, and ſpecially of papiſts: but for this time wherein I am rather to wet my finger, than to waſh my whole hand, onely to touch it. So it fel out with the prophets, when they put their trumpets to their mouths &amp; fought the Lordes battel againſt falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, then did the wicked moſt ſlaunderouſly charge them and defame them. So likewiſe fell it out with the Apoſtles when their ſound did ſound to the vtmoſt, and their voice was heard in moſt places: when their bowe was at a ful bend, and their arrowes did wound the mighty &amp; tame many: the more they preached the trueth and diſcouered vntrueth: the more they painted out &amp; perſecuted falſe Prophets and idolatrous ſpirites, the more were they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, their good name and heauenly doctrine ſlaundered, as new, not auncient: as ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, not catholicke: as hereticall, not true: as diueliſh, not diuine: as vtterly corrupt and no way tolerable. And as it fell out with the Prophets and Apoſtles, ſo hath it fallen out with vs in theſe our daies. For where wee are troubled with many falſe Apoſtles, who doe not only not conſent to the open trueth, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:17068:4"/> ſet themſelues openly againſt it and ſeek to withdraw others fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it: when to that purpoſe they caſt yet out their pamphlets, &amp; paper wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to winne the field of vs: where yet we do from time to time by the Scripture not onely teare their weapons, but withal diſcouer their cauſe to the world to their vtter diſcredit: in a word: when thus they ſee that they can no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner bid battle but that we aſſoon do foil them: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what do they but fal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which ſhould perſwade, to ſlaunderous reporting &amp; lying, not only againſt the perſons of men, but alſo for their ſakes againſt the manifeſt trueth profeſſed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: For euidence whereof at this inſtant not to trouble your worſhips w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infinit inſtance, I am content only to name their late cenſure &amp; later defence, wherein they fayling in iuſtifieng of their diuinitie nothing leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuine, haue fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon to vnreaſonable outrage againſt the good name and zeale of godly men. Howbeit for this point I need not to ſay much. For where there are too manie ſtiffe papiſts at large and diuers in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in priſon or rather in their paradiſe: if any man come to them of zeale and good will to worke ſome good among them: if to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he offer a diſpute and deſire a conference: either of preiudice to the cauſe they yeeld not
<pb facs="tcp:17068:5"/> thereunto: or if they doe, yet when they are brought to a <hi>non plus,</hi> and can ſay no more: what do they but fal to railing &amp; raging: what doe they but apply their hartes to wiſh euil &amp; their tongues to ſpeak worſe of God and his religion? We are by &amp; by without any premiſe concluded to be heretiques, no catholiques: new fellowes, no auncients: of <hi>Luther,</hi> not of <hi>Peter:</hi> of <hi>Caluin,</hi> not of Chriſt: no leſſe than reprobates: ſo that where they cannot match vs in reaſoning, they fall to vnreaſonable ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: and all their apologie and final but yet reaſonles reſolution is this, that they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, and we heretiques. Howbeit here by the way a retentiue is miniſtred againſt al this their manner of dealing: for ſith al here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, and amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g al other, papiſts were neuer more purſued by the force of trueth, it is no maruel, if with the Foxe they bee moſt faultie and filthy in their wordes againſt vs and our religion. Iuſt like Foxes, moſt vncleane when they are moſt chaſed. Whereas if wee would let them alone, and take them for religious rabbins: condemne our catholique verity for vncatholique hereſie, and take &amp; eſteeme their catholique hereſies for Apoſtolique verities, &amp; bend our knees to their Lord God the Pope and his deuotion, as we doe to God &amp; the only
<pb facs="tcp:17068:5"/> good religion, then ſhould we be their white ſonnes, and heare nothing but wel from them and among them. But where we bow to God and not to <hi>Baal,</hi> and tread their popes triple-crowne, indeede trouble-crowne in the duſt, &amp; take Chriſt alone for our catholique head: and no traditions of Rome, but his worde for our ful and alone direction, whether to beleeue or liue, thereof it is, that neither our profeſsion nor we for the ſame can heare any thing but euil of them. Thus they proue themſelues to be moſt vncleane, like the Foxe, when hee is hardly followed. And therefore what ſhall I ſay to end this point of the metaphor, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to pray: good God therefore purge them or els purge the land of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for what are they but Foxes? Foxes, and that not onlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are vncleane, but alſo crafty &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile like Foxes. For the Foxe is a crafty beaſt and he hath his holes and he wil hide himſelfe, and it ſhall be hard to driue him from one but that hee will finde refuge for the time in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet at length the good hunter takes him. Right ſo fales it out with hereticks, but ſpecially with papiſts: for they are crafty and ſubtile ſpirits, &amp; when we doe moſt perſecute and preſſe them with the trueth, yet they haue their ſhews &amp; ſtarting holes: they haue their
<pb facs="tcp:17068:6"/> diſtinctions, their ſhiftes, &amp; if one ſerue not, yet will they coyne ſome other colorably for the time to credit their vntrueth: whereby it comes to paſſe (by the way to mention a lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table matter) that for want of good hunters, this their ſophiſtry and Foxly diuinity ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth many ſimple ſoules in many places. But to come to the proofe of this point of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor. Thus they commend to the worlde their good workes vnder the name of merit: their merites vnder the name of grace: their penance vnder the name of a ſacrament: their worſhip of ſaints vnder the name of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: their maſſe vnder the name of Chriſtes ſacrifice: their praiers for the departed vnder colour of charity: their vowed ſinglenes vnder the name of chaſtity: their vnſatisfieng ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions vnder the name of godlines &amp; dutie. Thus they commend to the worlde their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of gods mercy vnder the name of godlie feare: their ignorantnes in ſcriptures vnder the name of Chriſtian ſimplenes: their pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages vnder the name of deuotion. Thus they commend till it come to luſt vnder the name of infirmitie and yet profitable, yea a mean meritorious, more therefore than expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient: their very ſtews vnder the name of euil, &amp; yet needful &amp; conuenient: yea rebellion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:17068:6"/> the name of catholique obedience, &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnder the name of merit. Thus they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for their purgatory gods iuſtice: for their posſiblenes to fulfil the law imposſible gods mercifulnes: for their abominable tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation the almighties mightineſſe. In a worde: thus they commend their ſenſings, their ſhriuings, their offerings, their purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engs, their ignorant praying, their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous adoring, their kisſing of the paxe &amp; ſuch like lies, toyes and vanities vnder the name of catholique and ancient cuſtomes. Thus they play the crafty Foxes and ſeeke to ſet a good colour vpon their doctrine moſt openly falſe and hereticall: vpon their practiſes moſt dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, perilous and tyrannicall. And though this were ſufficient to demonſtrate this point, yet to ſhew more to the proofe of the ſame. If we alleadge againſt their praiers to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted a principle of diuinity, that there is one mediator betwene God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus: they play the Foxes and run to their holes, they ſhift off the matter and ſaye: there is one mediator but not one only: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto when we anſwere that the particle (one) in that place is not only a particle of affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but of excluſion, as it is in the firſt place: Chriſt being our one and only mediatour, in
<pb facs="tcp:17068:7"/> whoſe name as there is one &amp; one only God to whom we may pray, they play the foxes &amp; run to their holes: they diſtinguiſh that indeed ther is one and one only mediator of redemption, &amp; that is Chriſt: but yet there are manie media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of interceſſion: whereas yet the ſcripture ſpeakes there of both, &amp; applies and appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates both to Chriſt: and they for their partes make the ſaintes not onely petitioners but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers: meriters &amp; that not only of temporal but of eternal things, &amp; that not only for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues but alſo for others. So likewiſe where we alleadge againſt their Popes ſupremacie a principle of Scripture: that Chriſt is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his temple, they run to their hole and play the Foxes: they diſtinguiſh that there is but one principal head of the Church &amp; that is Chriſt: but there is another miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al &amp; vicarial, &amp; that muſt be their Pope: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as yet the headſhip of the Church is proper to Chriſt, &amp; their pope by his title in this caſe, (if Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> were not deceiued, if the pope cannot erre,) indeed is not either top or toe of the Church. So likewiſe where againſt their iuſtifieng of luſt for no ſin, we alleadge a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of ſcripture: that euery tranſgreſſion of the law is ſin: &amp; withal the prohibition of the law, thou ſhalt not luſt: they run to their hole
<pb facs="tcp:17068:7"/> &amp; play the Foxes: that the apoſtle ſpeaks there of luſt with &amp; not without conſent: whereas yet the Apoſtle ſpeakes in general of al luſt: &amp; it were great folly once to dreame that euer the Apoſtle doubted whether luſt ioined with conſent were ſin or not. Thus to conclude, if any man pleaſe to run ouer their ſummaries &amp; queſtionaries: their old ſchoolemen or new men: nay to leaue al, if to this purpoſe a man reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber &amp; run ouer Maiſter <hi>Campian,</hi> that came into the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with a floriſhing antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with bidding of battell, with a crack &amp; catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſhew for al his fellow Foxes of Rome &amp; of Rhemes: yet where he was not only neerly aſſaied but eaſily preſſed with truth, what did he but play the poor Fox? he came into the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diuinity with fooliſh ſophiſtry, (what leſſe can I cal it?) in proofe and trial w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ridiculous and childiſh diſtinctions, and thoſe were his holes and in them he thought to haue kept himſelfe ſafe or at leaſt cloſe to the credit of his crack and to the deceiuing of the ſimple for the time, till treaſon had made the craftie concluſion, but al was too little: and (God be thanked) he proued himſelfe that way the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Fox that euer came among vs. But to end this point of the metaphor: I onely wiſh this, that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beware the craft of heretiques, but
<pb facs="tcp:17068:8"/> eſpecially of papiſts, of ſeminaries &amp; Ieſuites, who of al others play the Foxes moſt kindlie. And therefore for a caueat as for their olde ſubtil and yet ouerbold crackes that they are of the olde ſtamp: that they are catholiques: that they are the Church: that their Church cannot erre: that they only haue the right ſenſe of Gods woord: that they onely wiſh the good ſtate of the lande, the ſaluacion of your ſoules: her maieſties fauour and ſafetie: nothing leſſe (God ſaue her from them): al wel (indeede all il, as you all know too too well) to al that wiſh wel to Sion; take heed of them: for theſe &amp; the like bee but holes wherein the Popes Foxes ſeeke to colour out their cauſe and to couer their faithles creed, as demonſtration hath bin made and that oft to the world: and therefore to end this part of the metaphor, what ſhal I ſaie but once againe pray: good God therefore amend them or els make an ende of them: for what are they but Foxes? Foxes that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they are vncleane and craftie like Foxes, but alſo crafty and ſubtil to deuoure and deſtroy. For ſo doth it fal out with al here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques and ſpecially with papiſts. They come in ſheepes clothing: with faire titles &amp; tales: they wil appear like Angels of light: they talk of virginity, merit, abſtinence, hoſpitality, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:17068:8"/> al perfection, not onely of duty but of ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they tel the world, that no world was good but when they raigned: that then all things were plentiful: men charitable &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and what not? none liue wel but they, ſaie they: they faſt, they pray night and day, they go long pilgrimages: they puniſh their bodies and doe great penance: but whereunto tendes al this but to deceiue? theſe be nothing els but the falſe floriſh of a Phariſee, the Foxes ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry to beguile the ſimple: for aſmuch as they are nothing leſſe then that they would ſeem to be: they are no leſſe then Foxes. For to make the verie beſt of them, what are they but as naught as naught can make them? what are they but Foxes? in ſhew gold, in truth copper: in ſhew flowres, in proof weeds: in ſhew ſheep, indeed rauenous Foxes: oh what are they but Foxes? for what doe they ſeeke but euery waie and euerie day to deuoure the bodies and ſouls of Chriſtians? for what doe their perſuaſions to their religion moſt openly heretical? what doe their conſpiracies (now as you know and maie lament all) the verie comfort and onelie hope of them, moſt openly diabolicall ſay anie leſſe? for (to appeale to you al) what is it? reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion catholique or deuiliſh: to ſaue or to ſlaie the ſoules of men: to command men vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:17068:9"/> paine of an eternal curſe to beleeue that a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal man, the man of Rome, a prelate in title, in trueth the pilate of the woorld, is head of the church: that he cannot er: indeed to plurify the godhead, to make man a god: what religion is it that accounteth mariage in their inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent votaries as bad, if not worſe, then double adulterie? luſt without conſent no ſinne? good workes the merit of heauen? what religion is it, that ſaith: worſhip images, wher God ſaith: do not: but worſhip me only. Worſhip in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, where God ſaith do not: but worſhip me only in ſpirit and verity. Laſtly what religion is it or how can it bee good, that calleth Gods word darke, though light: the matter of ſtrife, though the woord of peace: imperfect without tradition, though the rule of al perfection: yea the ſenſe of the word only gods word, and their ſenſe the only true ſenſe, which yet is moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly falſe. Though this were ſufficient to proue this point, which I might amplify more at large, yet to adde a litle more: for this is not al nor almoſt anie thing to the largenes of the matter: nay alas what ſhal I ſaie of them? are not papiſts cockle? doe they not ſeek to deſtroy the corne? are they not thornes? doe they not ſeeke to pricke and teare the roſe? are they not dogs? do they not ſeek to deuoure the darling?
<pb facs="tcp:17068:9"/> are they not Foxes? doe they not ſeeke to waſt the vine of Ieſu Chriſt among vs? nay, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to you al: oh where had our corne beene? how not choked? oh where had our roſe been? how not rented? oh where had the darling of Chriſt been? how not deuoured? oh where had his vine been? how not waſted, if papiſts had obteined their perillous practiſes of old or of late among vs? oh then once againe to appeale to you al, what are they but cockle? what leſſe then the corne? what are they but thornes? what leſſe then the roſe? what are they but dogs? what leſſe then the darling? what are they but Foxes? what leſſe then the vineyarde of Chriſt our Sauiour? ſhal I ſay al (Right worſhipfull and dearly beloued) &amp; prooue al by that that you know &amp; may lament all? happie could papiſts haue thought themſelues by this time, if our natural Prince, our gracious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, our Queene, our Lilly <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the very life and comfort of vs al had bin torne in peeces: happie were they now, if forreiners could come in among vs: happie if there were nothing but killing &amp; murthering: in a woord happie could papiſts think themſelues, if they ſaw al your children and friends ſlaine before your faces, and you were all to followe after: happie, if there were nothing but fainting of
<pb facs="tcp:17068:10"/> thighes: nothing but foulding of armes: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wringing of handes: nothing but weeping, wailing &amp; woing among you: happy if the diuel &amp; his murthering ſeruantes could once diſpatch and diſplace you. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our gracious <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was like to bee torne: to this purpoſe they haue ſought her the glory of our land: to this purpoſe the catholiks of Rome are growen to bee cruell and grone to bee cutthroates: to this purpoſe they haue not long ſince attempted the matter: Good God therfore ſaue vs from them, for what are they but Foxes? and becauſe they are Foxes, therefore at this time I am (right worſhipful) to craue you to catch them. And ſo to omit the ſecond metaphor, becauſe the time would be too ſhort, I come to the matter. Catch (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) the Foxes &amp; the little, &amp;c. Wherein I note two points: a precept and the vſe. The precept in theſe wordes, take vs the Foxes, and the little Foxes: the vſe or end implied in theſe words: leaſt our vines, &amp;c. Touching the firſt point, to omit manie pointes and at this time onlie to note, 1. Who are to be catched: Foxes and little Foxes. 2. Who are charged to take them. 3. Who chargeth. For the 1. Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes and little Foxes are commanded to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: old therefore and young heretiques muſt
<pb facs="tcp:17068:10"/> be taken, none ſpared, whether great or little. For as leauen ſowreth the dough, though it be but little: as pitch defileth the cleane, though it be but little: as a canker eates and marres the bodie of man by little and little, though at the firſt neuer ſo little: ſo the Fox and little Foxe may waſt the good vine: &amp; therefore al Foxes are commanded here to be taken: al hereticks to be catcht, leaſt the Church of Chriſt doe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer daunger by them. But here alas what ſhal I ſay? for though al heretiques ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: though neither Fox nor litle Fox ought to be free but faſt: though the vine bee in peril of waſting by the fox though great, though litle: yet alas neither is little nor great Foxe made faſt but ſuffered free in diuers places. Nay, oh what may we lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but the freenes of Foxes? for what number of heretiques? what number of recuſants? what number of papiſts? to giue them their due and true name, what number of traitours are there abroad? abroad and not taken? or if taken, yet ſometimes enlarged? or if not inlarged, yet ſo viſited, where they are impriſoned, that manie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer find their paradiſe, til they come to the priſon? where I fear they want no maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ouerplus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fellow-foxes: where I fear they want no conference, where I feare, the Fox &amp; the little
<pb facs="tcp:17068:11"/> fox are neuer ſo faſt but that they do waſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vines of Ieſu Chriſt. But alas this ſhould not be ſo: and here the Fox and little Fox are commanded to be taken, that the vine of chriſt might be ſafer then ſo. Who are therefore to take them? who are to take care, that it maie not be ſo? ſurelie I take it, that this precept doth bind miniſter and magiſtrate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you (Right worſhipfull). For in both there ought to bee ſuch carefulnes ouer the vine, that neither Foxe nor little Foxe ſhould eſcape their nets, where the vine is in danger. Howbeit they are to catch them differentlie: the Miniſter by the woord, the Magiſtrate by the ſword: the one by loue, the other by feare: the one by ſoftnes, the other by ſharpnes: the one by perſwading, the other by puniſhing, if that perſuaſion may not preuaile. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing that, then in this our daie the light of the truth was neuer more light, and Chriſt ſo beareth his ſtars in his hande, that all men may eaſily ſee the old and onely true way that luſt not to be blind: and yet with our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries neither our Preaching nor Penning can any way preuaile, but that their whole trauel is by night and by day, by lande and by Sea, elſewhere &amp; at home here not only to dimme the light of Ieſu Chriſt by their falſe and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical
<pb facs="tcp:17068:11"/> doctrine, but alſo by force and violence to remoue the ſtars that are in his hand, that they may no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſhine vnto vs: nay ſith there is in them ſuch zeale to their hereſies: ſuch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the trueth, that they count themſelues euen no leſſe then halfe dead, that Sion lyeth not waſt in the duſt: yea and to that purpoſe aduenture not onely their lyms but their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catholicke liues: content to turne their name of catholickes for the name of vncatholicke cutthrotes; now by profeſſion and practiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing the ſweete name of innocent Ieſu for the traiterous name of <hi>Iudas</hi> to work out the matter, it belongeth to the magiſtrate, and to you to your power (Right worſhipful) to help that way, leaſt the vine of Chriſt doe lie waſt by the means: for the Lords ſake to catch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, for what are they but Foxes? whereunto the rather to moue you, I ſhal not neede to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you what the Fox hath attempted of old or of late againſt the vine, becauſe of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: all men doe know it, and al good hearts may lament and fear it, leaſt the Fox attempt the like any longer, if that hee bee not taken in time and preuented. But for this thus, it were policy and piety to keepe the vine ſafe: but this being ſo, neither policy nor piety but pitiles impietie to let the Fox free, leaſt the vine doe
<pb facs="tcp:17068:12"/> lie waſt. You know what I meane: you know I ſpeak trueth: and therefore for the Lordes ſake looke to your charge &amp; ſpare neither Fox nor litle Foxe, where you may come by them, but ſee that you catch them. Oh cut Papiſtes ſhort of liberty: for what are they but Foxes? In which caſe I do craue but your charitie, though dutie exact it. Howbeit if the light of Gods countenance bee deare vnto you, if the Golden Candelſticke of Chriſt be golden and glorious in your eies and among you, if your hearts bee glad to ſee theſe gladſome daies, wherein the Goſpel of Chriſt, the very power of God to ſaue your ſoules is preached vnto you: ſhal I ſaie al? if the ſtate of our gracious ſoueraigne and vnder her of Chriſtes deare Church be deare vnto you, then you ſhould of your ſelues and readily looke to the Foxe and little Fox that looks for the contrary: to catch them betimes &amp; to let them haue the reward of Foxes, leaſt they catch you before your time &amp; to your woe proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be Foxes vpon you: which day as they hope for, ſo if it ſhould com (which yet god forbid, as he hath forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe many years of his goodnes &amp; infinit mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) yet then you would wiſh, though too late, you had taken the Fox. It were beſt therefore for al magiſtrats to be wiſe in time, leaſt peril
<pb facs="tcp:17068:12"/> bring repentance when it wilbe too late: and therefore dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to enquire for foxes: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for papiſts: &amp; to let them haue neither liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor life, where the vine of Chriſt maie ſtand in danger of waſting by them. For that is the cauſe why this precept is giuen. Oh but there is ſmal loue in your lips, wil catholickes ſay: nothing but cruelty in your mouth wil others ſay: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I anſwere that ſo ſhal obiect &amp; that out of my laſt part, that ther is ſmal charity in them, whoſoeuer they are, that would haue the fox ſpared where there is danger leaſt the vine by the fox be waſted. For they that haue no loue to the vine may pitty the Fox: &amp; in very deede there is none that wiſheth the freedome of the fox, but he that wiſheth da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to the vine. But herein I need not to anſwer much: I appeal to you al: whether euer the vine of Chriſt were in greater peril of waſting than now it is? &amp; why? but becauſe the Fox hath bin too long ſuffered &amp; hath not by mercy &amp; patience bin wonne but waxed worſe, as experience &amp; too too late hath made lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table trial. Whereas if the fox had bin take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in time, his might &amp; malice had quite been cut off, and the vine of Chriſt had been in better ſafetie: but for this onelie thus I ſaie. You knowe and ſee all what miſchiefe hath come to the world, what daunger to the vyne,
<pb facs="tcp:17068:13"/> becauſe the Fox hath not beene taken from time to time: and therefore hereafter for the Lords cauſe delaie you no time but ſee that you take them. Let the vine of Chriſt be deare vnto you, and ſpare not the Fox, leaſt you loſe the vine. Oh ſpare vs not Papiſts: for what are they but Foxes? for this is the charity, that this my Text craueth of you: this is the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that yee owe to the vine: and if any ſpare the Fox to the daunger of the vine, that is no charitie but crueltie, and iuſtice wil be ſharpe to puniſh it in the daie of iudgement, when all men ſhal haue no iudge but God, who is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Who will bee ſure to ſmite home, if the Fox bee not catcht, that goeth about to waſt his vine, but ſuffered to worke his ſpite vpon the vine. And ſurely ſith our aduerſaries are ſo eger to choake the wheat of God, that they the tares: to hew downe his greene trees, that they the drie ſtickes: to corrupt his ſweete dough, that they the leauen: to ſlaughter his Lambes, that they the butchers: to waſt his vines, that they the Foxes of Sathan the God of this world may rule &amp; raigne once againe with their bel of Rome in the church of Chriſt: and bring in ſteede of knowledge, ignorance: in ſteed of light, darknes: in ſteede of truth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true tradition: in ſteed of Antichriſt, the diuel:
<pb facs="tcp:17068:13"/> and al to the vtter miſerie of your eſtate, that now is bleſſed and happie: ſith they ſlacke no occaſions to bring this about, but euerie daie and euery way doe gape and grone for the laſt daie of this your comfortable condition in Chriſt our bleſſed Sauiour, as of al others, ſo among al and aboue al, of you (Right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and others of your calling) I craue to your power a contrarie care: for the Lords wheat, that the tare doe not hurt it: for his ſweete dough, that the leauen of Rome doe not ſowre it: for his Lambes, that the bloodſuckers of ſathan: for his vine, that the Fox doe not waſt it. For (to appeale to the conſciences of you al) if they fight thus for darknes, oh what ought you to doe for the light? if they ſtriue thus for ignorance, oh what ought you to do for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? If they doe thus for hereſie, oh for the Lords ſake doe you no leſſe for the truth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal veritie of Ieſus Chriſt: if they for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, fight you for Chriſt: oh defend his vine and ſuffer not the Fox to waſt it. Oh ſaue the vine from Papiſtes: for what are they but Foxes? But how ſhal you ſaue it, you wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſaie: I haue anſwered and adde: permit them not free: take care to enquire and catch, and when they are taken, take care to keepe them from comming neere the vine. You haue
<pb facs="tcp:17068:14"/> authoritie to doe it: God and vnder him and for him our gratious Queene hath giuen you power to doe it: and if you ſhal vſe it (as dutie in theſe our daungerous daies doth earneſtlie beg it) the Fox I grant may curſe you, but the vine of Chriſt ſhal haue cauſe to bleſſe you for it. Al which I doe not ſay or vrge (Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful) ſo much to charge you with a dutie vnknowen, as charitablie to remember you of your dutie, which I know you doe know. For I doubt not but you know that God hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you Gods, and that you ought therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men and for men to bee Gods, that you ought therefore to be lights: enimies to darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and al the ſeruantes of ſathan the God of darknes: in a woorde, friends to the vine, but foes to the Fox: foes then to our vine foes, foes to Papiſts: for what are they but Foxes? Nay I hope that you haue a ſpeciall regarde of the vine and withal a good wil to worry the Fox. Onely therefore I am here to intreat you and that in the blood of Chriſt and bowels of his mercy, that this your godly care may increaſe: for the vine of Chriſt doth craue it, and if you remember neuer ſo little theſe our daies of danger, the ſubtil and the rauenous Fox him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of himſelfe doeth force it. Although I might remember you, that theſe words which
<pb facs="tcp:17068:14"/> ſound that way, are the words not of anie leſſe man then of <hi>Salomon</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt the true <hi>Salomon,</hi> who hath choſen to himſelf of al women but one virgine, of all birdes but one Doue, of all Doues but one Turtle, of all trees but the vine, &amp; that is his church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath ſuch an eſpecial care, that as he hath charged al men, ſo (among &amp; aboue al other) ſuch as are of your high calling to bee protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the ſame, to catch the Fox and little Fox, that hee doe not waſt it, to catch the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Foxes, that go about to waſt it. In fine, this is the charge that Chriſt heere giueth, Chriſt who gaue his life for his Church, his vine: Chriſt who ſhal iudge all: ſo that if either loue to his Church or feare of iudgement may preuaile, you are bound to doe to your beſt in this behalfe. Oh but ſome wil ſay it were wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for you to ſpeak ſomewhat for the Fox, or els the time may come, when the Fox will requite your fauour. Whereunto I anſwere, that indeed fleſh and blood taketh it to bee the beſt courſe to ſpare or at leaſt in ſome ſort to ſpeake for the Fox, but wiſedome commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and charitie craueth that neither Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter doe ſpeake for, nor Magiſtrate ſpare the Fox: and therefore Chriſt here requireth in the behalfe of his vine, that wee ſpare not to
<pb facs="tcp:17068:15"/> hunt and take the Fox, whereſoeuer, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he bee, that goeth about to waſt the vine. And as for that daie, which many men feare, indeed the Fox of Rome hopes to work it, but I hope we ſhal neuer ſee it: and yet if wee doe, our ſinnes haue deſerued it, and I would pitie the man moſt for his pitiful caſe, that hath ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Fox, and al to find pity. For no doubt he that pittieth the Fox that pittieth not but laboreth to waſt the vine, ſhould find either in that daie the Fox pitiles, and if he doe, iuſtly: or if not, yet one daie a God, that will bee ſure to puniſh the foxes friend and his vines foe. And therefore as for thoſe politiques whoſoeuer, that ſpare to catch the Fox that the Fox maie ſpare to catch them in his daie, when he coms to waſt the vine: that their policy is intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iniury to the vine, &amp; cruel dealing towards their owne ſoules, as without harty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance they ſhall finde and feele to their vtter ſmart, when the maiſter of the vineyard ſhall come to catch and to bind for euer al Foxes, al foxes frinds, &amp; foes to the vine. In a word: this their policy what is it but folly to be pitied to ſpare the waue, where the ſhip, the brier, where the flower, the wolfe where the ſheep, the Fox where the vine of Chriſt is in danger? nay to indanger al &amp; that to the vtmoſt: that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:17068:15"/> ſhip is drowned, yet the waue: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the flowre is faded, then the brier: when the ſheep is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, then the wolf: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vine is waſted, yet the Fox a profeſſed foe may proue a frinde: but oh politique, or rather fool, or rather foe to thy ſelfe whoſoeuer thou art: O pittiles policy maie the vine ſay, the verie next way to bring me to the waſt, thy ſelfe to the pray. Laſtlie to draw to an end. Perhaps it wil be yet obiected that the Foxes are many, mightie and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and therefore it wil be hard and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to catch the Foxes that are in the lande. Wherunto I anſwere, that indeed ſo it is, and a miſerie it is to conſider, that the Foxe is ſo great, ſo mightie and ful of malice: our fathers haue had trial before vs, and the Fox of Rome hath ſpared to attempt no attempt in this our accepted time to proue himſelfe no leſſe vnto vs. But here (Right w. and deare beloued to appeale to you al) how came the Fox to bee ſo mighty, but becauſe he was not taken in time? and becauſe pity to be pitied, (what leſſe may I ſaie of it?) hath made him mighty: and might hath made him the more malicious &amp; haſty to bring our vine to the waſting: therefore haue you (Right worſhipful &amp; others of your high calling) nowe the more cauſe to catch them, leaſt their might, and with their might, their
<pb facs="tcp:17068:16"/> malice doe increaſe and grow to further euill and woe among vs. God be thanked, where of late both his might and malice haue bin diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, the Foxe hath had ſome whelpes taken, and they haue found in iuſtice the due rewarde of Foxes. And ſith God hath beyond our deſert brought the perillous practiſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>re piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les purpoſe of ſathan by them to the light, and (as you al know) that as yet the great Foxe of Rome hath many whelpes among vs, as ſome of the principals are taken, ſo take you the care as far as you can, to hunt for the reſt. So wil you doe if the floriſh of the vine: if the vine of Chriſt be deare vnto you. So ſhal you doe what the true <hi>Salomon</hi> here craueth of you. In a word: you ſhall doe wel if you purpoſe it, but you ſhal do beſt &amp; god wil highly bleſſe you if you practiſe it. In the meane time to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you thus I ende: the time it ſelfe doth vrge it: for the Foxe himſelfe is rauenous: the vine it ſelfe doth craue it: for the ſtate thereof is daungerous: and <hi>Salomon</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt (who ſhal iudge vs al) doth here require it, in whoſe name therefore I end as I began: take vs the Foxes and little Foxes, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our vines and vine bloſſomes. <hi>To God the Father, the Son, and the holie Ghoſt, be al praiſe now and euer: Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17068:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
